Jeffrey Smykil /s'mɪk.əl/

은 He/Him

5912 N. Paulina, Unit 2W Chicago, IL 60660

617.485.4609

smykes.github.io

github.com/smykes

in linkedin.com/in/jeffsmykil

Skills

Computer Languages

JavaScrit/Node.js CSS HTML Python (Learning)

Databases

MongoDB (Working)
PostgreSQL (Working)

Tools/Frameworks

Git / Github

React

Express

Typescript

Mongoose

Bootstrap

MaterialUI

Tailwind

Flask (Learning)

Creative Tools

Inkscape Linearity Curve Pixelmator Figma CapCut Shotcut A New England transplant, former teacher, classically trained musician, and avid reader, software engineering is my second career. I enjoy creating tools that make people's lives easier through intuitive data-backed design with a strong focus on accessibility. I like getting dirty in the entire process and learning about different parts of a tech stack with which I am unfamiliar. With approximately ten years of experience in software engineering, I have experience leading teams, mentoring and coaching, and planning and architecting large portions of applications including APIs and database schemas.

Work Experience

Software Engineer | Discovery Education | 05/2023 - 02/2024 | Full time (Contract)

One of the largest educational technology companies in the world as a contractor, I helped develop the company's re-write of their digital Science Techbook focusing primarily on WCAG AA accessibility compliance.

- Streamlined code base to meet WCAG AA standards, leading to VPAT approval and enhanced user experience.
- Worked with a product team to develop features that met our customer needs, including orientation pages, and curriculum standards utilities.
- Enhanced features and fixed bugs through backlog refinement, resulting in reduced application tech debt and improved user experience.
- Worked with back-end developers to optimize the installation and maintenance of the Pendo platform, resulting in an improved onboarding experience for the end user.

Senior Software Engineer | Screencastify | 03/2022 - 01/2023 | Full Time

A start-up focusing primarily on the educational sector providing a suite of web-based video recording and editing tools allowing students to complete unique assignments, and teachers to provide informational materials and assignments for students.

- Worked on the license management team assisting in the development of the database schema, developing the user-facing interface in React, and writing database seeding scripts.
- Improved email delivery through the development of an emailing service using GraphQL, Postgres, and asynchronous task workers, leading to a more reliable communication platform for the company.
- Improved documentation process for the company by creating standardized guidelines for using Material UI and EmotionJS, resulting in a decrease in onboarding time for new developers and fostering a more efficient development environment.
- Guided team in enhancing component style libraries, leading to resulting in improved dissemination across teams
- Increased codebase cleanliness and consistency through the creation of CSS in JS linting rules.

Principal Software Engineer | Encyclopædia Britannica | 07/2017 - 03/2022 | Full Time

One of the oldest companies in the country Encyclopædia Britannica now focuses on consumer and education materials. As a principal engineer on the "Institutional Learning" team, I was pivotal in planning, architecting, and writing some of the company's flagship products including Launch Packs, Britannica School, Escolar Online, and Britannica Learning Zone.

- Collaborated with product and back-end developers to create an assessment platform, resulting in greater teacher satisfaction. Responsible for writing the majority of front-end code and planning service contracts.
- Developed and deployed fixes for accessibility issues, safeguarding the company's retention of several large contracts
- Partnered with UI/UX to create and disseminate new style guides via Story Book, contributing to design consistency and alignment improvement, ultimately boosting user satisfaction and product appeal.
- Led a cross-functional team of contractors and a junior product manager to successfully deliver an application for the pre-k market, resulting in a product used across the entire country of Brazil.
- Designed and implemented an in-house analytics platform, leading to more insightful reporting and decision-making.
- Mentored and coached several interns and junior engineers, helping them succeed in the company's environment.



Refrences

Available upon request.

Front End Engineer | L2 Interactive | 04/2015 - 07/2017 | Full Time

A consultancy company focusing exclusively on the arts sector, the company built websites for some of the largest arts organizations in the world including, but not limited to the San Francisco Ballet, the Australian Chamber Orchestra, and the Chicago Shakespeare Theatre. The company also offered integrated ticketing services through the Tessitura network.

- Built and maintained websites for some of the largest arts organizations in the world, writing custom code and using the company's proprietary CMS.
- Worked directly with customers to ensure that their needs and visions were being met.
- Was entrusted with working on-site with a company in Sydney, Australia to help prototype and launch their website

Full Stack Engineer / Designer | Rev4 Interactive | 11/2014 - 5/2014 | Full Time

The second employee at an early-stage startup providing an interactive second-screen experience for movie theater pre-rolls. Was responsible for mobile-first design, wireframes, and interactive demos, front-end, websocket connected backend.

- Created a websocket interface between the front and back ends allowing for timed transitions based on signals from projection hardware.
- Used Framer.js for interactive demos for potential clients.
- Designed and implemented the entire mobile interface
- Created games and polls for greater viewer engagement.

Software Engineer III, Ad Delivery Developer | PointRoll (Now Sizmek) | 05/2014 - 10/2014 | Full Time

An advertising company that allowed customers to easily create desktop and mobile advertisements for various industries and fields.

- Assisted in developing a web application to process advertising assets into a proprietary advertising format, resulting in an increase in throughput and enabling the team to handle a higher volume of ad conversions.
- Wrote and integrated new tests into the continuous integration system, resulting in enhanced code quality and faster delivery of features.

Front End Developer / Designer | Radianse | 10/2010 - 05/2014 | Full Time

A hardware/software company focused primarily on the medical industry that focused on providing analytics regarding staff and patient interactions, wait times, and resource locations for some of the most esteemed hospitals in the world.

- Developed a web-application for tracking equipment, patients, and staff, increasing user engagement and efficiency.
- Built a real-time dashboard and infrastructure tracking network connection health of over a thousand locations.
- Involved in front-end development, service contract creation, implementing front-end functional testing, as well as integrating client-side templating infrastructure.
- Created front-end for displaying timelines of asset locations, real-time mapping solutions.
- Responsible for uniting the front end into the continuous integration workflow.
- Created a real-time push interface for RFID card reading kiosks.

Volunteering & Leadership

- SciAnts Media | 03/2022 Present | Science Communication Outreach Coordinator
- Athletic Coach / Umpire | 2005
- College Information Technology Committee | 2000 -2003
- Music Educators National Conference Local Chapter | Public Relations Officer | 2003

Education

Bachelor of Music | K-12 Instrumental Education | Keene State College

Certifications / Relevant Courses

- K-12 Instrumental Music Education | 01/2004 06/2007 | State of New Hampshire Board of Education
- Moving from Bias to Inclusion in a DEI Journey Course | 07/2024 | Codeacademy
- JavaScript Foundations Professional Certificate | 05/2024 | Mozilla
- Introduction to Web Accessibility WCAG 2.1 | 05/2021 | Udemy
- Full-Stack Engineering with JavaScript | 08/2024 | CodeSignal